<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-12T13:11:41-05:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SLKone</title><subtitle>SLKone is a bespoke management consulting firm bridging Strategy, Leadership, and Knowledge to build lasting solutions.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Customers or Employees First?</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2023/09/28/Customers-or-Employees-First.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Customers or Employees First?" /><published>2023-09-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-09-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2023/09/28/Customers-or-Employees-First</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2023/09/28/Customers-or-Employees-First.html"><![CDATA[<p>In today’s day and age, many organizations and leaders find themselves struggling with serving two seemingly disparate goals: taking care of their employees first or taking care of their customers first. The first thought provoking question one may consider is – does it really matter? 
Having worked with countless organizations, we can assure you, it certainly does matter. First, we will explore some background into why this is a discussion at all. Then we will explore the significance of both customers and employees, lastly we will discuss strategies to find the equilibrium that can drive success.</p>

<p>Understanding Customers and Employees</p>

<p>Clients are typically long-term, strategic partners with whom a business engages in ongoing relationships. They may be corporations, organizations, or individuals who rely on specialized services, personalized attention, and a deep understanding of their unique needs. On the other hand, motivated and engaged employees are essential for delivering high-quality engagements that keep clients coming back.</p>

<p>The Client Perspective</p>

<p>Clients often require personalized solutions and a high level of intimacy. They require a deep understanding of their business, industry, and goals. Building strong client relationships requires investing time and effort into understanding their evolving needs and providing exceptional value. By putting clients first, organizations can cultivate loyalty, generate positive referrals, and foster strategic partnerships that fuel growth.</p>

<p>The Employee Perspective</p>

<p>Knowledgeable, skilled, and motivated employees are the backbone of any company. Their expertise is the foundation upon which client solutions are built. Engaged employees are more likely to deliver exceptional service, leading to satisfied clients who in turn are more likely to return for future projects.  Employees who are encouraged to learn and grow can transfer their knowledge to peers and junior staff, creating a culture of continuous improvement and innovation.  A supportive work environment and opportunities for career growth are essential for retaining top talent.</p>

<p>The Balancing Act</p>

<p>While prioritizing either clients or employees may seem like an all-or-nothing proposition, the key lies in finding a delicate balance. Successful organizations recognize that clients and employees are interconnected and that neglecting one can have consequences for the other. For example, a business may lose clients if it fails to address customer needs or provide satisfactory support. Conversely, a singular focus on creating a fun workplace culture can sometimes lead to a lack of structure where deadlines are not met and productivity dwindles (plus significant financial impact!).  Disgruntled employees can also be a cause for clients to look elsewhere.</p>

<p>Strategies for Striking the Balance</p>

<ol>
  <li>Create an Employee-Centered Culture: Prioritize creating a workplace culture that values and supports employees.  This includes offering competitive compensation, providing opportunities for skill development, flexibility and maintaining healthy work-life harmony.  More importantly people want to feel that their voices are heard; this means listening to concerns and acting on them.</li>
  <li>Develop Talent: Invest in training and development programs that empower employees to continuously enhance their skills. Encourage cross-functional training to foster a broader knowledge base within your team. This allows you to leverage knowledge across the board.</li>
  <li>Listen to Client Needs: While employees are essential, the ultimate goal for the business is client satisfaction. Develop a client-centric approach that focuses on understanding client needs, delivering quality results, and building strong relationships.</li>
  <li>Get Employee Feedback: Regularly solicit feedback from employees to gauge their satisfaction and identify areas for improvement. Act on their input to create a better workplace and enhance client service.</li>
  <li>Measure Satisfaction: Measure both client and employee satisfaction, using key performance indicators (KPIs) to assess success in both areas. Strive for equilibrium rather than favoring one over the other.</li>
</ol>

<p>Conclusion</p>

<p>In the business world, the question of what comes first, clients or employees, isn’t a matter of choosing one over the other. It’s about finding the right balance that maximizes client satisfaction and employee engagement. SLKone recognizes that these two elements are interconnected; happy employees are more likely to generate satisfied clients.
By fostering a culture of continuous improvement, investing in employee development, and maintaining a relentless focus on client needs, organizations can strike the delicate equilibrium that leads to long-term success, growth, and sustainability. In the end, it’s not a matter of choosing between clients or employees – it’s about optimizing both for the benefit of your firm and its stakeholders.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://slkone.com/files/SLKone_Article_Customers_or_Employees_First_2023.pdf" class="btn-filled" target="_blank">Download this Article as a PDF</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Isabella Doval</name></author><category term="Article" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In today’s day and age, many organizations and leaders find themselves struggling with serving two seemingly disparate goals: taking care of their employees first or taking care of their customers first. The first thought provoking question one may consider is – does it really matter? Having worked with countless organizations, we can assure you, it certainly does matter. First, we will explore some background into why this is a discussion at all. Then we will explore the significance of both customers and employees, lastly we will discuss strategies to find the equilibrium that can drive success.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recession - An Opportunity to Slingshot Your Business Past the Competition</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2023/02/06/Recession-an-Opportunity-for-Business-2023.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recession - An Opportunity to Slingshot Your Business Past the Competition" /><published>2023-02-06T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2023/02/06/Recession-an-Opportunity-for-Business-2023</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2023/02/06/Recession-an-Opportunity-for-Business-2023.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recession clouds are looming over the 2023 business horizon. The prevailing recessionary indicators do not fit exactly into classic economics—yet there is a real threat that we will soon talk our way into recession. While hunkering down to ride it out is a valid option, it is not a winning strategy.</p>

<p>Leaders who find opportunity and orchestrate a dynamic, strategic shift can defy the business climate and slingshot past the competition. The knowledge and necessary tools exist to exercise this agility if action is taken now.</p>

<p>The Current Climate</p>

<p>The US economy and the US consumer have been defying expectations. US GDP grew at an annual rate of 2.9% in the fourth quarter of 2022. Consumer spending continued to support GDP growth in 2022 despite the dual headwinds of rising interest rates and high inflation. The Industrial Production Index registered at 103.43 on December 31, 2022. While trending lower in recent months, it was still up from 101.76 a year prior.</p>

<p>Yet, geopolitical uncertainties, a hawkish monetary policy of raising interest rates and easing supply-side constraints to cool inflation should usher the US economy into a broad-based recession and drive-up unemployment rates. The paradox of this foreordained recession is that many business leaders continue to grapple with job openings for key positions due to the historically low jobless rate and severe labor shortage.</p>

<p>A true business leader cannot afford to stand still at this crossroads and become a roadkill. Today’s business climate demands a new level of agility. The timing is right to simultaneously sense, seize, and shift the business to meet economic realities while staying compassionate, factual, and inspiring.</p>

<p>The Traditional Playbook</p>

<p>Facing recessionary headwinds, business leaders typically hire external consultants or dust off the standard recipe that has worked in the past. Their to-do list will be:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Control Costs – lay off 10-15% employees</li>
  <li>Manage Cash Flow – accelerate collections and slow down payments</li>
  <li>Diversify Revenue Streams – add new customers</li>
  <li>Communicate – overcommunicate the threat of recession</li>
  <li>Micromanage – emphasize reporting and reviews</li>
</ol>

<p>Sadly, this stale recipe is not going to work in this new age recession. It is more likely to alienate customers, damage the supply chain, and demotivate and overwork employees who are under a microscope creating busy-work reports instead of working effectively.</p>

<p>A new playbook is required but that’s not enough. This business environment requires a high level of dexterity and attentiveness. The traditional playbook is like driving a car with an automatic transmission that eases operation and facilitates making adjustments—the radio, the AC—along the way. A new approach to the business environment is more like a stick shift transmission, requiring a higher degree of participation from an alert driver executing precision steering. Leaders can’t rely on the automatic but must grab the controls to take charge, using a new playbook to seize new opportunities and accelerate past the competition.</p>

<p>A New Playbook for Business Leaders</p>

<p>SLKone recommends rethinking your approach to recession with these five, key actions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Double click on the right customers and products in your portfolio</strong>. Historically companies in certain industries take a direct hit during recessions: automotive, construction, financial services, manufacturing, retail, and tourism. These can impact other industries to a lesser degree such as consumer staples, healthcare and pharmaceuticals. Avoiding customers in the former and securing customers in the latter may have worked intuitively in past recessions.</p>

    <p>The new playbook that we recommend departs from these generalizations. The key here is double clicking. We mean identifying and ‘clicking’ on the customers in your portfolio that will come out as winners despite the recession and determining how your products and services will be essential to their success story. Many SLKone clients have successfully managed their customer-product portfolio complexity with rapidly developed perspectives that connect through ‘order to cash’ processes with operational and financial parameters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pursue meaningful innovation</strong>. While recession-triggered, smart, cost reduction can kill off meaningless intellectual and non-commercial ‘hobbies’ within an organization; avoid strangling all innovation in pursuit of reduced costs. What is required now is a shift to innovation that creates lasting success for your customers. Engage customers and vendors in purpose-driven innovation that aligns the interests of your ecosystem. The best innovation will not be a groundbreaking idea but recognition of a problem and a practical process tweak that allows the value chain to do more with less waste. At SLKone, our teams engineer performance metrics for our clients that help them rethink their value chain and pivot away from siloed innovation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Enhance real-time information with smart-knowledge creation</strong>. Relying solely on real-time information is a view in the rear-view mirror that can create panic and make operators numb. Smart, data-driven, decision tools are the best ally for effectuating this playbook. Avoid long reviews of real-time reports. Each SLKone client engagement is crafted to build leave-behind tools for ongoing, informed, decision-making by your business leaders and teams.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Inspire employees</strong>. Instilling recessionary fears that paralyze the employee pool is the last thing a business leader wants. Yet, the old school playbook does exactly that. The headlines are going to be bad. SLKone does not recommend ignoring the facts: what we suggest is shifting the employee dialog from inert incapacitation to empowerment. Their insights need to be integrated into what the business is and should be doing with its customer-product portfolio. Employees should be encouraged to act on innovative tweaks and be rewarded for that. Chances are that recent pandemic experience has established remote work protocols. Rather than forcing employees to be physically present in offices, avoid the unproductive transit times and improve work life harmony. Focus on empowerment and support rather than threats of doom.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Execute the Slingshot</strong>. The purpose of creating the new playbook is not merely to survive a recession but to shoot past vulnerable competition and secure a permanent lead. Like the dramatic slingshot maneuvers in Formula 1 or in cycling, businesses can execute a similar move. The key is positioning, waiting for the right moment, and then applying an extra burst of energy to get past the competition. Steps 1-3 help a business position itself for the opportunity, and the inspired employee pool in Step 4 provides the collective energy needed to slingshot past the competition.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>While this playbook can be universally applied, it becomes a business imperative in the prevailing business landscape by rallying the team for better outcomes rather than grimly hoping to minimize losses.</p>

<p>Predicting the ‘if,’ ‘when’ and ‘how’ of recession is a wasteful debate. It is a myth that ostriches bury their heads in the sand, but businesses are known to demonstrate that behavior during tough times—with catastrophic results. Recession, when and not if it hits, is going to require a better approach. The SLKone playbook enacted with support from motivated employees, enables business leaders to seize the moment and catapult the business ahead—from recession to opportunity.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://slkone.com/files/SLKone_Article_Recession-Opportunity_2023.pdf" class="btn-filled" target="_blank">Download this Article as a PDF</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Arun Shukla</name></author><category term="Article" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recession clouds are looming over the 2023 business horizon. The prevailing recessionary indicators do not fit exactly into classic economics—yet there is a real threat that we will soon talk our way into recession. While hunkering down to ride it out is a valid option, it is not a winning strategy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Are you Ready for Process Mining?</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2022/12/15/Are-you-Ready-for-Process-Mining.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are you Ready for Process Mining?" /><published>2022-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2022/12/15/Are-you-Ready-for-Process-Mining</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2022/12/15/Are-you-Ready-for-Process-Mining.html"><![CDATA[<p>Process mining can address common business challenges and provide actionable value. Consider how your organization can benefit using the data in your ERP, CRM and other systems.</p>

<p>Why Process Mining?
Processes define the activities an organization conducts. Absence of standard process definition or lack of adherence to standard processes creates suboptimal outcomes. Process mining uncovers opportunities for value accretion. It is the single most important source of extracting value that an organization can pursue.</p>

<p>What is Process Mining?
Most business activities can be viewed as processes supported by server and cloud-based systems. These systems, such as enterprise resource planning (ERP), customer relationship management (CRM), and supply chain execution (SCE), generate event, audit, or history logs.  Process mining uses these logs to perform rapid, detailed analyses of business processes based on existing data, not aspirations.</p>

<p>The primary process mining steps are discovery, conformance, and enhancement. Discovery reveals current business processes and major process variations. Conformance compares a process model with an event log of the same process to reveal how they match-up. Enhancement is an analysis of a data-driven model for process optimization.</p>

<p>Where does Process Mining Effectuate Significant Benefits? 
The following ubiquitous business challenges have prompted organizations across a wide variety of industries to turn to process mining techniques.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Business Process Improvement. Embedding a culture of continuous improvement is imperative in today’s dynamic landscape. Process mining skips lengthy process mapping efforts, using real data and algorithms to quickly make existing processes clearly visible—allowing enhanced governance and oversight. Initiatives are no longer burdened by bias supporting visibility and real-time feedback on as-is processes.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Operational resiliency. At the process and systems level, organizations need the appropriate guard rails to mitigate operational and financial risk of their most critical activities. Process mining conformance techniques help auditing and compliance initiatives through complexity reduction, enhancement of organizational capabilities, and KPI development by comparing as-is processes to the intended design. This allows the organization to understand how well they can handle disruptions to their process.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Digital transformations. During the pandemic, digital transformations accelerated, enabling key strategic initiatives and, frankly, survival. Employees and consumers have adjusted to remote work and life. Process discovery enhances the impact of digital transformations by reducing implementation delays and risks due to misunderstood processes, manual routing, and process gaps.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Process automation. Process mining creates visibility and builds understanding of hotspots where robotic process automation (RPA) and task automation will deliver the most value. Process mining has proven to reduce the risk and implementation time of RPA projects.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Are you ready for process mining?
The time needed to apply process mining is surprisingly short—when the data are there. According to Gartner Research, 80% of organization’s process mining effort and time are spent locating, selecting, extracting, and transforming the process data. Internal process mining and data cleansing expertise, missing process functions, and a complex IT landscape can hinder process mining efforts.</p>

<p>At SLKone we help clients gain insights into their processes and then properly utilize them. The framework in the graphic below helps explain where process mining techniques can benefit an organization most. It integrates the three challenges—business process improvement, audit and conformance, and process automation—with three process mining techniques—discovery, conformance, and enhancements, along a path to process and systems maturity. The italicized activities improve readiness for the process mining techniques and  levels of process and system maturity.</p>

<p><img src="http://slkone.com/images/process-minining-image.png" /></p>

<p>Celonis Process Mining Software helps us turn your data into actionable, highly visual information that is of value across your organization.  As management consultants with exceptional data skills, we collect and make sense of data for process mining applications. We also can deploy a suite of open-source tools to evaluate an organization’s process health, diagnose key issues, and develop and deploy process documentation and training. We help organizations use process mining to guide development of real-time operational dashboards that provide visibility and guardrails for key stakeholders within the organization’s ERPs and CRMs. We help clients using process mining to guide decisions and implementation related to digitization and automation.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://slkone.com/files/SLKoneArticle_Are-You-Ready-For-Process-Mining.pdf" class="btn-filled" target="_blank">Download this Article as a PDF</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Bernardo Jaccoud</name></author><category term="Article" /><category term="Process-Design" /><category term="Operations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Process mining can address common business challenges and provide actionable value. Consider how your organization can benefit using the data in your ERP, CRM and other systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making EVA Work for You: Practical Steps to Economic Value Add</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Making-EVA-Work-for-You.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making EVA Work for You: Practical Steps to Economic Value Add" /><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Making-EVA-Work-for-You</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Making-EVA-Work-for-You.html"><![CDATA[<p>Organizations, whether publicly listed corporations or private equity portfolio businesses, have a common goal of accelerating value creation for their investors. No other metric comes close to Economic Value Add (EVA) as a universal measure for value accretion. However, while it is well understood at the senior leadership level, it can remain an abstract concept for frontline management. While lack of financial literacy has been cited as the primary reason for the lack of adaptation, the onus lies on a company’s leadership to connect the dots for shareholders, sponsors, and the workforce to take EVA from boardrooms to shop floors.</p>

<p>EVA as a universal measure of value creation has had a mixed history. Its ascendance in the late 80s has been attributed to Stern Stewart &amp; Co., and more recently it reemerged after Institutional Shareholder Services (ISS) acquired EVA dimensions, a business intelligence firm founded by Ben Stewart. However, the concept was first introduced to the corporate arena in the 1920’s by General Motor Corporation.</p>

<p>EVA had its hay day in the late 1980’s and early 1990’s but with the emergence of asset light internet era technology businesses in the late 1990’s EVA lost its luster. However, its decline was evident prior to that with purist practitioners applying accounting adjustments (as many as 164) to arrive at “real” EVA. Whirlpool Corporation debated 140 adjustments before implementing EVA. Coke made 15 adjustments to simplify before its launch. Similarly, John Deere simplified the count of adjustments to improve acceptance. Georgia Pacific, felt that the measure did not do justice across divisions. Also, a myopic perspective on EVA discouraged early adopters from investing in smart long-term initiatives perceived as excessive investment vs. game-changing improvements.</p>

<p>EVA is an elegant concept – it assesses the performance of a company and therefore its leadership team when a business generates wealth for its shareholders over and above its cost of capital. The calculation shows how and where a company created wealth, through the inclusion of balance sheet items. EVA can be expressed as follows:</p>

<p><b>EVA = NOPAT – (WACC * capital invested)</b>        <br />
Where NOPAT = Net Operating Profits After Tax<br />
WACC = Weighted Average Cost of Capital<br />
Capital invested = Equity + long-term debt at the beginning of the period<br />
and (WACC* capital invested) is also known as finance charge</p>

<p>This simple equation forces business managers to be aware of assets and expenses when making decisions. EVA aids capital efficiency by indicating how to make good investments more productive as well as highlighting when to avoid bad investments. It also shows when and how to redeploy capital from the bad investments to the good. In such ways, it raises capital efficiency without sacrificing growth. Unfortunately, the benefits of EVA are hard to realize when the definition of assets and capital to financial measures restrict its ability to be understood to only the finance function within a business.</p>

<p>At SLKone, we believe that the disconnect between EVA as a financial function’s metric to an enterprise-wide metric can be addressed through concerted efforts that require:</p>

<h4 id="disaggregating-financial-measures-to-operational-measures---what-can-managers-do-to-avoid-the-black-box-syndrome-of-eva">Disaggregating financial measures to operational measures - What can managers do to avoid the “black-box” syndrome of EVA?</h4>

<ol>
  <li>Unpack the concept of EVA into its components. Dupont charts are a time-tested tool to build a decision tree of interconnected economic, financial, and operational drivers and metrics. <br /></li>
  <li>Business measures such as profitability should be split into functional metrics such as revenue drivers and customer acquisition cost metrics for the sales function. Do make the linkages with causal metrics such as response time and first-time resolutions. Similarly for capital charge metrics, working capital, inventory, and capacity utilization can be the drivers.<br /></li>
  <li>Highlight specific measures where changes yield the most value. Limit them to a practical number of 3-5 metrics per function.<br /></li>
  <li>Ensure that the person or the group being measured can control the trajectory of the metrics.<br /></li>
  <li>Rather than using the theoretical definition to calculate EVA, managers should make practical measures that are best suited for the business. As an example, subtracting operating costs and capital charge from the revenue drivers is a good proxy for economic profit and value accretion.</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="communicating-the-concept-to-improve-financial-literacy---what-can-managers-do-to-translate-the-abstraction-of-eva-into-a-language-that-all-employees-can-understand">Communicating the concept to improve financial literacy - What can managers do to translate the abstraction of EVA into a language that all employees can understand?</h4>

<ol>
  <li>EVA is a natural concept. No rational person will ever expect to be able to borrow money for free nor expect to make money if the returns do not exceed the borrowing costs. Managers need to humanize EVA from business speak to a practical and common-sense concept.<br /></li>
  <li>Build an X-Matrix (Hoshin Kanri) that transcends the organizational tiers.<br /></li>
  <li>Linking variable compensation to controllable leading drivers to EVA drivers will help adaptation. <br /></li>
  <li>Include frontline workers in building the DuPont performance tree.<br /></li>
</ol>

<p>EVA can begin to take life within the organization if the leadership adopts the KISS (Keep it Simple, Silly) principle. Do not be afraid of shaping your own EVA equation, one that works best for your organization. Make EVA deliver its promise by having the frontline workers not just the corporate leadership fingerprint the Dupont charts.<sup>1</sup></p>

<p><sup>1</sup><a href="https://www.strategy-business.com/article/12756" target="_blank">Strategy+Business: Creating Value Through E.V.A.- Myth or Reality?</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Arun Shukla</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="November 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Monthly Edits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Organizations, whether publicly listed corporations or private equity portfolio businesses, have a common goal of accelerating value creation for their investors. No other metric comes close to Economic Value Add (EVA) as a universal measure for value accretion. However, while it is well understood at the senior leadership level, it can remain an abstract concept for frontline management. While lack of financial literacy has been cited as the primary reason for the lack of adaptation, the onus lies on a company’s leadership to connect the dots for shareholders, sponsors, and the workforce to take EVA from boardrooms to shop floors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why EVA Expectations Aren’t Always Realized in Transactions</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Why-EVA-Expectations-Aren't-Always-Realized-in-Transactions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why EVA Expectations Aren’t Always Realized in Transactions" /><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Why-EVA-Expectations-Aren&apos;t-Always-Realized-in-Transactions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Why-EVA-Expectations-Aren&apos;t-Always-Realized-in-Transactions.html"><![CDATA[<p>This newsletter is devoted to the pursuit of Economic Value-Add (EVA) in business – how it is useful, its impact, and how it’s used in businesses. At the high-level, EVA will reveal anticipated levels of economic impact from making decisions, and in this instance, the accretive (or not) nature of a transaction. Similarly, after arriving at an EVA calculation, leaders can assess the impact one transaction may have on the business versus another as capital is generally not limitless and decisions must be made. So, with a solid metric like EVA in place – why is the anticipated EVA not always realized post transaction?</p>

<p>EVA is comprised of two primary components: a) net operating profit after tax (NOPAT) (though many PE backed groups may review this on both pre- and post-tax bases) and b) the finance charge with the significant component representing the amount of capital invested in a transaction. When assessing a transaction and planning for the impact, the NOPAT must be estimated including planned synergies, required investments, and the anticipated performance of the business. The finance charge will include assumptions as a result of the transaction and may require a change in the capital structure – and a change therefore to the WACC – as well as estimating any transaction related expenses which would be included in the amount of capital invested in a transaction.</p>

<p>If we are focusing on the two primary components of EVA, how then can we not realize the anticipated EVA? Simply, estimates of the impacts, needs, and performance of transactions are often quite wrong. In most organizations, if the team has become bullish on a transaction or particularly likes the team being acquired, the performance will be over-estimated, the costs and expenses needed to integrate will be higher than planned, and performance variations will be explained away without updating estimations and expectations of the business.</p>

<p>The business of integrating companies together is taxing – both from the physical and emotional component as well as the capital required to do so. Planned acquisitions and integrations include budgets and expected costs to integrate a business, but often underestimate the costs. These costs should be included in the finance charge (capital invested) component of EVA for an acquisition. However, if these estimates are too low initially, the capital investment estimate will be artificially low, and the EVA metric will reflect a higher value than is realistic. These transaction related expenses must be analyzed for each transaction – leveraging historical information – but also taking into consideration the nuances of an individual transaction.</p>

<p>An area where many underestimations have been occurring in recent history is for legal expenses. With an increased transaction volume nationally, legal resources are harder to come by. Supply-demand principles reflect the costs of legal services will therefore increase – which is occurring – but also transaction timelines are increasing and may cause other transaction related expenses to increase with the delayed timelines. For instance, Quality of Earnings reports may need to be updated, advisor groups may be retained for longer periods, and even interest rate changes may occur impacting the WACC.</p>

<p>So, what can businesses do? First and foremost, have an honest conversation regarding the expectations of a transaction. Deconstruct the estimates and assumptions for the transaction and challenge them. Secondly, develop a standard, appropriate methodology for estimating transaction expenses with realistic timelines, expenses, and support requirements. Third, stress-test business models on anticipated NOPAT (or even just NOP) to reflect realities of future performance and with any changes because of the transaction. Last, ensure the advisors you are working with are versed in the transactions being contemplated, constructively challenge your teams on estimates, and work with them to develop realistic expectations of the transaction.</p>

<p>At SLKone, we have assisted both corporate and PE-backed clients with over thirty transactions in the last four years. We have focused on assisting teams with planning for their transactions and with integration implementation and go-forward business changes. If this sounds like something your business would benefit from, please reach out to learn more today.</p>]]></content><author><name>Phil Lynch</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="November 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Monthly Edits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This newsletter is devoted to the pursuit of Economic Value-Add (EVA) in business – how it is useful, its impact, and how it’s used in businesses. At the high-level, EVA will reveal anticipated levels of economic impact from making decisions, and in this instance, the accretive (or not) nature of a transaction. Similarly, after arriving at an EVA calculation, leaders can assess the impact one transaction may have on the business versus another as capital is generally not limitless and decisions must be made. So, with a solid metric like EVA in place – why is the anticipated EVA not always realized post transaction?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Licking the Data Spoon: Leveraging Insights From Existing Data Before a Digital Transformation</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Leverage-Insights-From-Exisiting-Data-Before-a-Digital-Transformation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Licking the Data Spoon: Leveraging Insights From Existing Data Before a Digital Transformation" /><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Leverage-Insights-From-Exisiting-Data-Before-a-Digital-Transformation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Leverage-Insights-From-Exisiting-Data-Before-a-Digital-Transformation.html"><![CDATA[<p>As we approach the holiday season, I recalled one of my favorite activities as a kid: helping bake holiday cookies. The best part was being able to lick the mixing spoons, an early tase of the treats to come. Similarly, digital transformations are in progress or being contemplated by nearly every organization, looking to drive efficiencies and uncover new insights into their business, these businesses are “licking the spoon”. While their promise is strong, there are opportunities that exist today for these organizations to utilize advanced analytics tools to get a taste of post-digitization life before adaption. This sounds great, but there are tools and techniques that work better in this environment than others, plus precautions and prerequisites that must be considered before that first taste. Even more so, these approaches can really be a contributor to EVA (covered more thoroughly in this newsletter) as the analytics can yield operational improvements and profit generation.</p>

<p>A pre-digital transformation organization still collects a significant amount of data that can be used in advanced analysis. Traditionally we have found two hurdles to using this existing data to its fullest potential. First, data controls are not always in place, and second, data exists in various, siloed areas. Poor data quality has always been a limitation of applied advanced analytics, but this is exacerbated in a pre-digital organization for several reasons. The primary factor is a lack of input controls. Open text fields serve as a stop gap to collect data based on someone’s desire at one point of time. Open data fields lead to multiple data issues, including non-standard and inconsistent entries. An example of this would be a customer name that can be entered as both ABC Co. or ABC or ABC company. This issue can be solved through several techniques, like fuzzy matching, using a controlled data field as a proxy (i.e., shipping address instead of customer name) or a mapping of non-standard field data. The key takeaway here is that while data may not be as good as it would be under future circumstances, creative solutions exist to use existing data in advanced analysis. Issues only exist when this is ignored, and erroneous outputs and insights can result.</p>

<p>The second issue, data in various areas, is another reason organizations aren’t taking advantage of advanced analytical capabilities. This issue has been resolved in some respects by the adoption of data warehouses, but some of the most interesting data sets are not generated internally. Historically, tying data sets together has been cumbersome both by a lack of a data key (transaction number, order number, etc.) as well as the tools available to connect the data sets. Excel certainly has its uses but, when it comes to connecting large data sets (the preferred method of non-data scientists), it has its limitations. By utilizing tools like Python and independent databases, it is now possible and efficient to tie together multiple disparate databases.</p>

<div class="emphasis">
  <p><strong>Recent Experience</strong><br /></p>

  <p>SITUATION: An eCommerce based distributor was seeking to reduce their SKU count on their primary site to reduce the cost of maintenance and improve site navigation.  The management team had performed an initial analysis but was concerned on the SEO metric impact from cutting SKUs, i.e. Low volume sales items might be driving site traffic.</p>

  <p>WHAT WE DID: SLKone, in collaboration with the clients marketing team combined sales and order data from an internal ERP with Google Analytics data on number of sessions, time of session, search results, and click through rates.</p>

  <p>THE RESULTS: Combined data set allowed for a unique analysis that accounted for volume, profitability, and site traffic contribution;  60% of the lowest performing products could be rationalized while impacting only 10% of sessions and 2% of users.</p>
</div>

<p>A commonly held belief by management teams and organization sponsors is that advanced analytics and the insights they drive are something the organization can only use and achieve once a transformation has been performed. The tools and processes to perform advanced analytics exist and can be applied to the organization right away to identify unique insights. Keep in mind, however, that these analyses are highly customized to the situation and are often difficult to replicate within the organization, so this is not an alternative to transformation. However, the insights gained and obstacles overcome performing this type of analysis can point the way for transformation initiatives. Organizations that don’t wait to utilize their data to the fullest will gain a key advantage in building enterprise value.</p>

<p><a href="https://slkone.com/contact/">Reach out</a> to learn more about SLKone’s application of advanced analytics and the impact they have had for our clients.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrew Klemm</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="November 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Monthly Edits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As we approach the holiday season, I recalled one of my favorite activities as a kid: helping bake holiday cookies. The best part was being able to lick the mixing spoons, an early tase of the treats to come. Similarly, digital transformations are in progress or being contemplated by nearly every organization, looking to drive efficiencies and uncover new insights into their business, these businesses are “licking the spoon”. While their promise is strong, there are opportunities that exist today for these organizations to utilize advanced analytics tools to get a taste of post-digitization life before adaption. This sounds great, but there are tools and techniques that work better in this environment than others, plus precautions and prerequisites that must be considered before that first taste. Even more so, these approaches can really be a contributor to EVA (covered more thoroughly in this newsletter) as the analytics can yield operational improvements and profit generation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving Shareholder Value through Economic Value Add</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Improving-Shareholder-Value-through-Economic-Value-Add.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving Shareholder Value through Economic Value Add" /><published>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Improving-Shareholder-Value-through-Economic-Value-Add</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/11/17/Improving-Shareholder-Value-through-Economic-Value-Add.html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last few years, Private Equity (PE) firms have seen exceptional returns on their portfolios and, coupled with an influx of investor capital into these firms, we have seen mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;A) transactions grow significantly. According to data gathered from S&amp;P Capital IQ, the last three months (Jul’21 – Sep’21) aggregated deal amount for US private equity investments totaled $243B in 2,841 transactions for an average deal size of $85M. Compare this to the same period in 2019 where the aggregated deal amount was $78.5B with an average deal size $45M, this represents a ~3X growth in M&amp;A transaction dollar volume and a 90% growth in the average deal size. There are undoubtedly several factors for this increase in transaction volume, but one major driving force of attraction to the PE space is the excess returns when compared to public equity indexes such as the S&amp;P or DJIA.</p>

<p>As shown in the table below with data as of March 2018, Cambridge Associates conducted a study on 1,500 private equity funds including buyout, growth equity, and subordinated capital funds, and compared their returns to common indices.<sup>1</sup></p>

<p><img src="https://slkone.com/images/EVA-index.jpg" alt="Data for Strategy Success Graphic" /></p>

<p>Generally speaking, the private equity index outperformed other common indices, but this becomes even more solidified as we look at longer time-horizons. So, how do private equity funds consistently deliver higher returns and assure that they are maximizing shareholder value? As a proven partner to numerous private equity companies, we believe measuring Economic Value Add (EVA) and focusing on improved performance of this metric delivers the best results.</p>

<h4 id="measuring-economic-value-add-eva">Measuring Economic Value Add (EVA)</h4>

<p>In a related article, my colleague Arun Shukla, describes an elegant approach to evaluating value creation using EVA. For more information on this approach please read Arun’s article in its entirety, but to summarize, EVA’s equation of NOPAT – (WACC * Capital Invested) helps measure how effective leadership is at driving value creation and deploying business capital.</p>

<p>Breaking down the components of EVA, net operating profit after tax equals EBIT * (1 – tax rate). The next part of the equation, capital invested, can be calculated as total assets minus current liabilities. Finally, weighted average cost of capital (WACC) is made up of two components which are the cost of debt and cost of equity to the firm. Once these components have been calculated, the economic profit of the business can be measured effectively, however, measuring EVA is only the tip of the iceberg. The leadership team must be able to unpack the results of the EVA calculation, adjust capital deployment to maximize returns, and devise strategic initiatives to improve operating profit.</p>

<h4 id="target-success--not-financial-results--to-improve-profit">Target Success – Not Financial Results – To Improve Profit</h4>

<p>This time of year, in the late third quarter or early fourth quarter, companies are solidifying their budgets which often include aspirational profit growth and a long list of spending requests to achieve their growth targets. Instead of trying to predict next year’s results based on a bottom-up view and spending requests that are likely to be cut 10-30%, we find it’s more effective to focus on improving outcomes for customers and stakeholders of the business. A few questions which can help develop a strategy for delivering these outcomes are:</p>

<p>•	What are the key challenges faced by the business and their customers, and what initiatives will drive the most growth in the coming years?<br />
•	Based on the above, how should resources (capital and human) be allocated? What is the optimal mix between maintaining existing products, innovating new products, expanding sales and marketing channels, or developing internal talent?<br />
•	Further, to which geomarkets should these resources be deployed and at what velocity?</p>

<p>The approach described herein is similar to an x-matrix, or a Hoshin planning matrix, which aligns long-term goals with specific targets to improve in order to execute on the strategy. Bridging the strategic initiatives with resources and targets in such a manner not only enables transparency in the process, but also creates accountability that transcends the entire organization.</p>

<p>At this point, it’s important to circle back to the budget and create a plan that is adaptable and easily refreshed. In recent years, we have seen a black swan event in COVID, market volatility, supply chain crises, and other factors that make budgets quickly irrelevant. No one can predict the future with complete accuracy and it’s therefore instrumental to refresh a budget on a routine cadence, performing a BVA with business leaders and functional budget owners monthly or quarterly. In these reviews, targets tied to your strategic initiatives should be evaluated and the necessary adjustments made to continually maximize EVA.</p>

<p>In a world of increasing complexity and information available at our fingertips, it can be difficult to know the right measures to evaluate a business and the associated levers to pull to effectuate change. We believe focusing on EVA will drive the best returns for shareholders, and following a decisive, strategic approach to capital investment will accelerate the value creation. This comes full circle as NOPAT will be improved through topline growth and an optimized cost structure. Unpacking all the components of EVA and establishing the stringent processes is not easily, but realizing the growth attained by using this approach makes it well worth the effort.</p>

<p><sup>1</sup><a href="https://www.cambridgeassociates.com/" target="_blank">Cambridge Associates</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Casey Matthews</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="November 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Monthly Edits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the last few years, Private Equity (PE) firms have seen exceptional returns on their portfolios and, coupled with an influx of investor capital into these firms, we have seen mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;A) transactions grow significantly. According to data gathered from S&amp;P Capital IQ, the last three months (Jul’21 – Sep’21) aggregated deal amount for US private equity investments totaled $243B in 2,841 transactions for an average deal size of $85M. Compare this to the same period in 2019 where the aggregated deal amount was $78.5B with an average deal size $45M, this represents a ~3X growth in M&amp;A transaction dollar volume and a 90% growth in the average deal size. There are undoubtedly several factors for this increase in transaction volume, but one major driving force of attraction to the PE space is the excess returns when compared to public equity indexes such as the S&amp;P or DJIA.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Get the Most Out of Your Data for Strategy Success</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Data-for-Strategy-Success.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Get the Most Out of Your Data for Strategy Success" /><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Data-for-Strategy-Success</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Data-for-Strategy-Success.html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>

<p>Strategic planning for your business is an elaborate process detailing where the business is now, where we want it to be in the future, and how we plan to get there, with potential obstacles considered. It is an intricate structure of information containing high-level goals and defining where each aspect of the business lies in achieving those goals. However, we need a way to measure and quantify each of these aspects to track how the business is progressing towards its goals with the current strategy.</p>

<p>Data from a wide array of sources is at the heart of evaluating business strategies, and when used correctly, will provide an assessment of current efforts and give insights to when it is time to realign business strategy. For business leaders, years of tribal knowledge and domain expertise alone is not enough to build a well-performing business strategy. Leveraging data, coupled with years of experience, allows business leaders to create a strategy to perform in their current conditions as well as is adaptable when a pivot in strategy is required due to disruptions and changes in the business landscape.</p>

<p>It is easy to be clouded by confidence in an existing strategy. Likely, hours of work and planning across multiple business units went into the strategy currently in place with leadership support. But the same strategy may be ill-performing, obsolete in the current conditions, or implemented incorrectly. Data is the resource that grounds business leaders to understand what is happening now. Leveraging this resource allows business leaders to evaluate existing strategies and adjust where necessary based on current conditions instead of emotional attachments to what has worked in the past.</p>

<p>Still, it is much easier to understand the importance of data in the strategic planning process than it is to implement it. Outlined below are some crucial prerequisites to incorporating data into a business strategy and checkpoints for where and when data can tell us a realignment in strategy is necessary for future success.</p>

<h4 id="aligning-data-strategy-and-business-strategy">Aligning Data Strategy and Business Strategy</h4>

<p>First and foremost, a sound data strategy is needed before insights can be gathered from your data. A data strategy details the collection, organization, analysis, and delivery of data across your organization to support your business objectives. Within each component, the people, processes, and technologies involved should be captured to ensure data is governed properly and responsibilities are clear. Your data strategy is ultimately driven by the overall business strategy, and it is critical that the two are aligned.</p>

<p>If data is not aligned with business strategy, there will be a significant gap in evaluating and tracking the current approach. This leaves business leaders in the dark, with only perceived gut feelings and prior knowledge to gauge if a business strategy is successful. Similarly, a misaligned data strategy may provide erroneous insights to the performance of the business which leads to poor decision making across the business. Over time, confidence in the insights diminishes and data is seen as a less valuable asset to the business.</p>

<p>An important step in aligning data with business strategy is determining what data is required to measure the performance of initiatives. In achieving this, a caveat to understand is that existing data collection efforts may not be enough to satisfy requirements and may not be the correct data to model and evaluate strategic aspects of the business. Business goals should be concise with metrics identified to measure performance before determining what data will be used to support the initiative.</p>

<h4 id="access-to-quality-data-across-the-organization">Access to Quality Data Across the Organization</h4>

<p>An additional aspect of incorporating data in your business strategy is to ensure business leaders have a simple and reliable way to access reporting and analytics which provide the information to evaluate strategic initiatives across the organization. Data may be dispersed across an array of systems, each with different primary business unit owners. Aspects of the business strategy will certainly touch multiple areas of the business and leadership will need to track progress in all areas, both individually and collectively. When information is siloed within a specific business area, other areas or functions cannot easily access the data required to measure the impact of a strategic initiative. Moreover, business areas outside of the siloed data rely on ad-hoc requests to connect data points and generate insights. Without a process in place to connect disparate data sources and validate the combined data, we may see completely different results from similar analyses with no way to know which provides the highest quality results.</p>

<p><img src="https://slkone.com/images/Data-for-Strategy-Success-figure.jpg" alt="Data for Strategy Success Graphic" /></p>

<p>Recently, we worked with an ecommerce business who was having cost increases passed along to them from suppliers. Additionally, management thought their prices were much lower than their peers and therefore suffered from lower profitability. In their normal process, the company’s product management team would perform spot checks or just apply a blanket price increase. However, leveraging their data, SLKone assisted with integrating specific cost increases as well as developed an algorithm to identify which products and customers were best suited for any additional price changes. SLKone leverage the data the company had been collecting, supplemented by management guidance, our experience, and external data sources to develop an approach which was shared across the organization – brining sales, product management, marketing, and operations together to collaborate on the approach.</p>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<p>So, not only is data relevant and necessary to a business’s strategy, but when properly aligned and accessible, businesses are better equipped to execute new strategies, have the tools to evaluate existing strategies, and can adjust strategies due to improved visibility of impact. If your organization would like to produce smarter insights by leveraging data to evaluate business strategy and realign where necessary, SLKone can help. Reach out to learn how SLKone can help you integrate data into your strategic planning and create versatile bespoke solutions to make your strategy smarter and adaptable.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://slkone.com/files/SLKone_Article_Data-for-Strategy-Success_2021.pdf" class="btn-filled" target="_blank">Download this Article as a PDF</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Patrick Gibson</name></author><category term="Article" /><category term="September 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Process-Design" /><category term="Operating-Model-Design" /><category term="Featured" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Monthly Edit: Effective Brand Strategy Begins with Culture</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Monthly-Edit-Brand-Strategy-Begins-with-Culture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Monthly Edit: Effective Brand Strategy Begins with Culture" /><published>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Monthly-Edit-Brand-Strategy-Begins-with-Culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/16/Monthly-Edit-Brand-Strategy-Begins-with-Culture.html"><![CDATA[<p>Effective brand strategy is an influential aspect of any business and can give your company an edge in an increasingly competitive marketplace. But branding can wear many faces and assume many definitions, which also makes it a complex strategy to implement and track.</p>

<p>At its foundation, branding should reflect your company culture; or rephrased, culture should inform branding. When building a branding strategy, take a step back and look at the characteristics that define your organization. The values, traditions, beliefs, and behavioral dynamics that make up the core of your workplace should be the driving force for your most effective and authentic branding strategy.</p>

<p>Branding is not just who you are, but how you run your business. At SLKone, we’ve created a bespoke management consulting firm built with a focus on standing apart from the stigmas of partnering with consultants. Our culture differentiates our company from industry counterparts through commitment to our five pillars: firm of the future, professionally rewarding, financially successful, work life harmony, and giving back to the community. As a company, we weigh the impacts of every action we take against those five pillars to decide on next steps. As a result of these philosophies, we are known to our clients as partners rather than hired hands. There is a mutual understanding that our approach won’t be to hand a client a singular cookie-cutter product, but a solution custom-fit to their needs, while remaining confident in a successful output. That is now our brand.</p>

<p>Universally, branding is thought of as a factor of growth. Brands informed by culture create organic growth. The value of an attractive business culture can be leveraged to attract new business, retrain current business relationships, and even grow your workforce. Who you are and how you run your business has become your greatest growth asset.</p>

<p>Even for inorganic growth, some of the biggest concerns come through cultural alignment. There can be no success in acquisition without focusing on and integrating culture. The two parts cannot work and grow in unison without having common morals, cultures, philosophies – or at least a path to get there. The most efficient solution to rebranding post-acquisition, is aligning culturally before thinking of the external brand.</p>

<p>The current state of our world is forcing many businesses to take a step back and look inward to redefine who they are and how they differentiate themselves from competitors. The company culture you create and the impact you want to have on the world around you inform the unique branding strategy that will drive your most successful and rewarding path forward.</p>

<p>At SLKone, we are taking this to heart. As part of our internal reflection, we identified changes we want to make to better reflect our company culture and how we represent ourselves. We will soon be launching a new logo, redesigning our website, and updating our external approach. Specifically, you will see a linkage to our approach to working with clients, focusing on their most critical outcomes, and partnership with their teams. Our work, for our clients, is performed collaboratively, spans multiple areas of business, and is focused on ensuring we deliver value and generate enterprise value. Please stay tuned and share the journey as we continue this evolution.</p>]]></content><author><name>Dustin Fidaleo</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="September 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Monthly Edits" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Effective brand strategy is an influential aspect of any business and can give your company an edge in an increasingly competitive marketplace. But branding can wear many faces and assume many definitions, which also makes it a complex strategy to implement and track.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Spotlight Interview: LeAnne Stewart</title><link href="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/15/Spotlight-Interview-LeAnne-Stewart.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spotlight Interview: LeAnne Stewart" /><published>2021-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/15/Spotlight-Interview-LeAnne-Stewart</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://staging.slkone.com/2021/09/15/Spotlight-Interview-LeAnne-Stewart.html"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PeoGW6_B7R0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
<p><br />
<i>Note: The following transcription represents highlights of our interview with LeAnne Stewart. Full-length commentary is available in the video above.</i></p>

<p>Today’s topic is around rebranding, pivoting, adapting, growing – both personally and professionally. LeAnne Stewart is the Chief Financial Officer of Axia Women’s Health, one of the largest healthcare organizations in the US solely focused on Women’s Health. During LeAnne’s tenure they have expanded to serve in over six states and continue to grow. LeAnne leads not only the finance and accounting functions, but revenue cycle, IT, and more depending on the needs.</p>

<p><b>Q: Thanks for taking the time to speak with us today. Can you share a bit of your background, how arrived at Axia, and how you’ve grown and changed throughout your career?</b></p>

<p>A: I am the eldest of three sisters and went to an all-girl’s school, a women’s college. Then I headed off to career adventures in public accounting. I’ve been CFO of a couple of multi-billion dollar public companies and have since been the CFO of a handful of private equity sponsored companies, most recently in healthcare services. I landed at Axia because women’s-centric missions are super important to me. When I was approached about the opportunity, I thought it would be a chance to continue my career in a different way – different challenges for a company like this versus companies I’ve worked with in the past – but also allow me to double down on women’s-centric missions. We are a women’s healthcare company. We are unique in a lot of ways and are focused on providing an all-inclusive healthcare opportunity for our patients. I love what we are doing and what we are building.</p>

<p><b>Q: It’s been fun to work alongside, assisting and cheering you on! Given your background, have there been any pivotal moments in your career or life that have led you down this path?</b></p>

<p>A: I say this, and it doesn’t sound professional, but there is an element of me making it up as I went along. I was the first in my family to go to college and I had to figure it out by myself. I have approached my career in a similar fashion in that I’ve been opportunistic and observant of what is going on around me, and to some degree, followed others because I didn’t know what I was doing. From all of it, I have no regrets. I’ve enjoyed all the twists and turns and learned a lot along the way, but it’s really been about taking advantage of the opportunities that were presented.</p>

<p><b>Q: Good advice for anyone. How different have the changes been as you’ve gone through your career regarding industries, leadership types, etc.</b></p>

<p>A: Every situation is naturally different, but there are often common themes. I started at EY, and I had just about every type of client from an industry perspective, but also size. One thing that’s been a hallmark for me since then, is that I really appreciated those different opportunities. If I think about when I earned my accounting degree, accounting is accounting. Then I got my MBA from the Wharton School, and finance is finance. How you can apply accounting and finance, and then experiences beyond that, is what I think is fun. Learning about different companies, and what makes them tick, has been a fun part intellectually.</p>

<p><b>Q: Reflecting, I imagine some of that is advice you give to your team or others in how to adapt in their careers – is that fair?</b></p>

<p>Yes, that and the previous question on being opportunistic. Combine that with wanting to continually learn. I’m a big believer that life is one long experience in learning and being curious and asking questions you might be nervous of asking. We all hear there’s no such thing as a stupid question, but we all worry about asking a stupid question – just ask it. Even in my role today, I ask questions because I can pretty much guarantee there is someone else in the room that wants to ask it and they just don’t. And if someone thinks it’s a stupid question, well then that’s their problem and not mine, I’ve learned something.</p>

<p><b>Q: Today’s business environment is not the same as it was even five years ago, and people entering the job market may need to be nimbler and more adaptable. From that, what potential changes do you see in the future as we think about the office of the CFO, healthcare, and other industries?</b></p>

<p>A: There’s no question the world is continuing to move faster and faster all the time. So being nimble in how you think about things, problem solve, and make decisions is really important. The world is much more data-driven now than earlier in my career and that’s a fabulous thing. Decisions made by data are important, but you also need to be practical and let your gut kick in sometimes, so you don’t drown in analysis. At some point, you have to say, “I have what I need”. CFOs are continually challenged to expand outside the traditional CFO role, focused on finance. Most CFOs today that are effective and enjoy their jobs have their fingers on a lot of different things and their ears open. You have to be at the table with the other members of the executive team thinking about where the company is going, how to drive it in that direction, how to prioritize, etc. You must have a strategic operations hat and a lot of other talents to add to your overall effectiveness as CFO.</p>

<p><b>Q: Echoing the data remark, you implemented a decision support function at Axia. The concept of using data-driven decision making exists in healthcare and other industries you have worked in. Do you see anything else coming that others need to be looking out for?</b></p>

<p>A: Everyone realizes the cost of healthcare in the US is untenable. So, there is an increasing level of focus on how do we be more thoughtful around the cost of healthcare, delivering the care that’s needed, in the most cost effective way, and also taking care of the patients. That’s a force that exists now and will continue to spiral and grow. You see more types of companies and capabilities entering the healthcare space that will influence what it will ultimately look like. I remember when I first joined the world of healthcare, people remarked that the pace of change was remarkably slow. It may still be true, but it’s getting faster and faster all the time. That is the challenge and focus for all of us. How do we widen the conversations around healthcare, its delivery, and effectiveness such that we can continue to improve beyond where we are at right now.</p>

<p><b>Q: Bringing on stakeholders such as payors, providers, and management entities, all focused on the same mission?</b></p>

<p>A: Exactly, it has to be all of those constituencies working together. No one person or entity or aspect is going to solve it all. We have to be working together collectively, and frankly, there need to be some conversations people don’t want to have around value, and is it worth it, and those are thing people don’t like to think about or talk about when it comes to their healthcare.</p>

<p><b>Q: Turning it around, as an advisory shop focused on helping good companies get better and adapt their business models for change, how do you think service providers can really stay relevant for their clients?</b></p>

<p>A: The greatest benefit third-parties can bring are outside views and perspectives. It can be easy to get wrapped up in your own stuff and not be aware of what else is going on, to bring in new ideas and say, “have you thought about this?”, or “have you looked at that?” is an important part of what a company like yours can do. Certainly, SLKone has helped on specific, tactical things, being a resource where we needed help. Having confidence in a third-party provider to fill roles, and help you think through what it should look like, being a thought partner for what a company can be in a year, or two years.</p>

<p><b>Q: Some of those opportunities may not exist for someone entering the workforce now. Are there any characteristics you think about when you look at hiring someone entering now?</b></p>

<p>A: Yes, several things. I mentioned curious earlier today – that is important to me. Courageous is another one – we talked about adaptability – being able to adapt and go with the flow in your job is important. A person will grow and develop as an individual, the company will benefit from the talents that you have that may not have even been identified yet – or the organization hasn’t identified they need. At Axia, our COO coined “being comfortable with ambiguity”. I am hiring for what a role really should be because we are still figuring it out. The people joining have a role in building and creating alongside me.</p>

<p><b>Q: Do you think there’s any influence or component of a company’s brand?</b></p>

<p>A: I don’t know that I’ve thought about it, but I would say yes. I would have jumped more to culture, but the two are intertwined in a significant way. Axia has a culture of creativity and that is embedded in our brand and how we go to market.</p>

<p><b>Q: Do you think COVID-19 had any impact on the brand at Axia?</b></p>

<p>A: For those of us that work at Axia, I believe it will have influenced our view of Axia and consequently what our brand means. To the external party, we wanted to ensure our patients felt safe. Obviously great care, but we needed to make sure they felt safe. COVID-19 has embedded that in our brand in a way that may have not been there before.</p>

<p><b>Q: Any last thoughts you would pass along to executives, leaders, or anyone even coming up in their careers?</b></p>

<p>A: Embrace it, roll with it, have fun. You never know what life is going to bring to you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Phil Lynch</name></author><category term="Newsletters" /><category term="September 2021 Newsletter" /><category term="Spotlight Interviews" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Note: The following transcription represents highlights of our interview with LeAnne Stewart. Full-length commentary is available in the video above.]]></summary></entry></feed>